YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 2. Predecessor Organizations and National Board
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES II. NATIONAL BOARD
  The National Board Nominating Committee was in charge of selecting two candidates for each of the officer's positions of the Association: President, Vice-Presidents, Secretary, and Treasurer. The selections were forwarded to the National Nominating Committee (see SERIES IV) which selected a single slate of officers for presentation at the National Convention. In some years, the National Board Nominating Committee was responsible for selecting the delegates to World Council; in others, the task fell to the National Nominating Committee. The National Board Nominating Committee also recommended Convention voting delegates from among the National Board and national staff; and nominated Honorary National Board members.
  Minutes of the National Board and Executive Committee, often with the associated attachments, make up the bulk of this series. As the "representative and executive" committee of the national association, the minutes are invaluable for understanding the policies and programs of the national organization and how the membership and focus of the organization developed. The records in this series are especially valuable for gaining any understand of the organization during the 1970s and 1980s since very few other records survive from those decades.
  Microfilmed Records, 1906-75 only
  Microfilmed records include National Board and Executive Committee minutes and reports, 1907-75; general and committee materials; biographical files on Board and Staff members; materials about various reorganizations of the Association, its offices and departments; and reports of the National Board.
  Microfilmed records of the National Board and Executive Committee can be found under:
  National Board and Executive Committee
  Subject Files
  National Board
  Original Format Records, 1906-2001, 12 linear feet
  [see Original Format Records Folder List]
  The bulk of the series consists of minutes and reports of the National Board and Executive Committee, 1906-2001. Attachments are sometimes included with the minutes.
  Other materials include rosters, memos, reports, financial statements, and other related material, and Emissaries, the newsletter for former members of the National Board. The bulk of these additional materials were created between 1988 and 2000.
  Records of Committees and Task Forces included in this series are those appointed by the National Board that were not associated with departments or divisions of the national staff. Department/division committee records are filed in other record groups.
  General National Board materials (including committees and policies) are filed at the beginning of the series followed by materials related to meetings.
  The minutes of National Board and the Executive Committee are intermingled. Executive Board minutes were circulated to the full Board as an attachment to its minutes. This means that Executive Board minutes are filed with the meeting materials for the succeeding National Board meeting.
  National Board orientation materials are filed in SERIES II. Training in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM.
  National Board reports to the membership at Conventions are filed in RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES.
  Taped portions of a few National Board meetings dating from the late 1980s and 2000 are in RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIAL. Also included are some Board orientation tapes.
- SERIES III. NATIONAL COORDINATING BOARD
  The National Coordinating Board succeeded the National Board as the central governing body of the YWCA in 2002. Executives from Community YWCAs launched a "Change Initiative" in 1998 in frustration with the lack of responsiveness and leadership from the National Board; they determined that thorough-going reform and a decentralized national organization was necessary to answer the problems that had long dogged the YWCA. At a special convention convened in 2000, the membership approved the plan of the Change Initiative to establish the YWCA as "now a bottom-up rather than a top-down organization." They liquidated the national office in New York and relocated some staff members to Washington, D.C., who would now be responsible for advocacy and fostering a national presence for the YWCA. They affirmed regional councils as the new site for the coordination of YWCA work. The regional councils would establish programming priorities and become responsible for dues allocations and requirements of affiliation for local association. The National Coordinating Board, its duties much reduced from those of the National Board, would be composed of representatives of the Regional Councils. The National Coordinating Board also resulted from the dire financial straits of the National YWCA, and it facilitated a reduction of staff and office while decentralization further removed the onus of program development from the national organization.
  Original Format Records, 1998-2002, .5 linear feet
  A few early National Coordinating Board records were received with materials transferred to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2003. These include early meeting materials, general information and publicity about the reorganization, and financial records.
  The early records of the National Coordinating Board, which began meeting in 2002, are closely tied to the Change Initiative. Materials are filed in SERIES II. REORGANIZATIONS in RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY.
  Additional information can be found in Convention files for 1998 and 2001 in RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
- SERIES IV. BOARD OF TRUSTEES
  The Board of Trustees controlled and managed any "real" property and moneys held in trust by the National Board. It was composed of at least nine members, a majority of whom were to be men. Nominated by the National Board, they were elected by the Board of Trustees to serve a 6-year term, on rotating basis. The Trustees are unpaid.
  The Board of Trustees records contain information about Association finances; purchase, sale, or transfer of National Board properties; endowments; and various committees with some financial responsibility. Included is information detailing budgets, deficits, and the financial effects of the two World Wars and the Great Depression on the work of the YWCA. Included are: minutes, agendas, rosters, and correspondence. Records from the 1990s, include preparatory materials and reports for meetings.
  Microfilmed Records, 1907-1975 only
  [see Microfilmed Records Reel list]
  Records related to the Board of Trustees can be found on the microfilm under:
  Board of Trustees
  National Board, Trustees
  Original Format Records, 1907-2000, 1.25 linear feet
  In addition to the Minutes and Reports, the paper records also contain general and committee rosters, correspondence and meeting materials, 1988-98.
  Materials related to budget and finance and buildings and properties owned by the National Association can be found in SERIES III. FINANCE AND DEVELOPMENT and SERIES II. BUILDINGS AND PROPERTIES in RECORD GROUP 3. GENERAL ADMINISTRATION.
  Additional budget materials can be found in National Board minutes and reports in SERIES II of this Record Group and in the Program and Budget Committee records in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
- SERIES V. NATIONAL NOMINATING COMMITTEE
  The National Nominating Committee (also known as Nominating Committee, and Convention Nominating Committee) was responsible for developing a slate of candidates for National Board; President, Vice-Presidents, Secretary, and Treasurer of the Association; and Convention Committees for the elections held at Convention. It also presented candidates to serve as U.S. representatives to the World YWCA and, at times in the history of the Association, nominated members and chairs for other standing committees.
  Up through the 1920 Convention, all of the Nominating Committee's business was transacted during the course of the Convention. Nominees were solicited on the first day, a slate was assembled in succeeding days, and put to a vote at the end of Convention. In order to secure more diverse representation, procedures were changed so that the Nominating Committee, elected at the close of one Convention, worked in the interim between Conventions to gather nominations from the entire YWCA membership, research the candidates, and offer a slate with accompanying information about their experience and qualifications at the following Convention. This slate became the publication Who's Who on the Ballot.
  Candidates for Association officers (president, vice presidents, secretary, and treasurer) were submitted to the National Nominating Committee by the National Board Nominating Committee. Board of Trustees candidates were submitted to the National Nominating Committee by the Nominating Committee for the Board of Trustees.
  The records of the National Nominating Committee present much evidence of the YWCA's efforts to achieve diversity in its leadership. The Association's desire to include all of its membership is reflected in a nominating process that struggled to find representation from all geographic regions of the country, and variety in terms of age, race, ethnicity, and, in later years, sexual orientation.
  Types of materials include rosters, proceedings/minutes, manuals, biographical information on candidates, memoranda, meeting logistics, nomination packets, and meeting packets.
  The early work of the Committee (up to 1948) is only documented within the records of Conventions. In addition, there are no records beyond those that are part of Convention records for the years between 1973 and 1985. Probably due to its rotating membership, the amount and breadth of the material varies considerably Convention to Convention. Some years have good demographic and biographical data about candidates and revealing information about the Committee's decision-making process.
  Microfilmed Records, 1906-70 only
  In the Subject Files, under 'Convention' are materials about and by the Committee which are part of Convention mailings, reports, and proceedings.
  Original Format Records, 1948-98, 1.5 linear feet
  [see Original Format Records Folder list]
  Surviving paper records in this series date back only to 1948 when the Committee for the 1949 Convention began its work.
  The records are arranged chronologically by convention cycle. Where applicable, biographical data about candidates is arranged alphabetically.
  Convention records in RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES contain reports on candidates, and election results, as well as Who's Who on the Ballot, the publication prepared for Convention delegates with information about each candidate's qualifications and experiences. In addition, some Convention Committee and Convention preparation records contain discussions of the role and activities of the National Nominating Committee.
- SERIES I. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Series Descriptions for historical and scope and content notes.
  - International Board
    - General and History, 1873-1932, n.d. (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - Conference Reports and Journals, 1871-1905 (Box 78, Folder 2-9)
    - Constitution, n.d. (Box 78, Folder 10)
    - Minutes, reports, and correspondence, 1891-99 (Box 78, Folder 11-15)
    - Minutes, reports, and correspondence, 1900-06 (Box 79, Folder 1-6)
    - President's Journal, Sep 1905-Dec 1906 (Box 79, Folder 7)
    - Publications
      - The International Messenger
        - bound copies, Vol 1, no. 1-12 - Vol. 4, no. 1-6 (Apr 1894-Sep 1897)Vol 6 (Apr 1899-Mar 1900) (Box 80, Folder 1-3)
        - unbound copies, Vol. 1 - Vol. 3, no. 1-3, Vol. 3 no.6-12 - Vol. 5, Vol. 6-7; Vol. 8, no. 3-12 (Apr 1894-Jun 1896; Sep 1896-Mar 1901; Jun 1901-Mar 1902) (Box 81, Folder 1-15)
        - Index to Volume 8 (Box 81, Folder 16)
        - Miscellaneous loose pages (Box 81, Folder 17)
      - The Bulletin, 1903-06 (Box 81, Folder 18)
    - Conference reports and journals: duplicate preservation copies, [DO NOT USE] (Box 82)
  - American Committee
    - General and History
      - Miscellaneous, 1892-1901 (Box 83, Folder 1)
      - Scrapbook, 1886-1905 (Box 83, Folder 2)
    - Annual Report and Convention Reports, 1886-1904 (Box 83, Folder 3-15)
    - Annual Report and Convention Reports, 1905-06 (Box 84, Folder 1-3)
    - Convention circulars, programs, and correspondence, 1886-1906 (Box 84, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1904-07 (Box 84, Folder 5-13)
      - Young Men's Christian Association, 1891-92, 1896 (Box 84, Folder 14)
    - Directories of member associations, 1887-1906 (Box 85, Folder 1-2)
    - Minutes and Reports
      - 1891-92, 1899, 1901-Apr 1904 (Box 85, Folder 3-12)
      - May 1904-07 (Box 86, Folder 1-12)
    - City Department
      - General, 1897, n.d. (Box 86, Folder 13)
      - Silver Bay City Conference, 1905-06 (Box 86, Folder 14)
    - Eastern Committee: minutes, 1902, 1904-06 (Box 86, Folder 15)
    - Foreign Work
      - General, 1897-1905, n.d. (Box 86, Folder 16)
      - American Department of the World's YWCA
        - Committee of the American Department: minutes, 1902-06 (Box 86, Folder 17-19)
        - Correspondence, 1903-06 (Box 86, Folder 20-22)
        - Financial Statements, 1904-06 (Box 86, Folder 23-24)
        - Scrapbook, 1895-1906 (Box 87, Folder 1)
    - Industrial and Extension Work, n.d. (Box 87, Folder 2)
    - Secretaries' Training Institute: reports of weekly prayer meetings, 1907 (Box 87, Folder 3)
    - State Work, 1885-87, n.d. (Box 87, Folder 4)
    - Student Work
      - General, 1883, 1886, n.d. (Box 87, Folder 5)
      - Silver Bay Student Conference, 1905-06 (Box 87, Folder 6)
    - Publications
      - Brochures and pamphlets, 1891-1905, n.d. (Box 87, Folder 7)
      - YWCA Quarterly: unbound copy, Vol. 1, no. 1-4 Nov 1888-Jun 1889 {continues as The Evangel}, [see also first bound volume of The Evangel] (Box 87, Folder 8)
      - The Evangel
        - Unbound copies (incomplete, but includes issues missing from bound copy), 1889-Jun 1892 (Box 87, Folder 9-11)
        - Unbound copies (incomplete, but includes issues missing from bound copy), Sep 1892-1906 (Box 88, Folder 1-8)
        - Bound copies
          - Most complete copy, Sep 1889-Dec 1906 (Box 89, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Monaghan Mills YWCA scrapbook, 1904-06 (Box 89, Folder 2)
      - Bay View (Michigan) Summer Conference scrapbook, 1891 (Box 89, Folder 3)
  - Merger of Predecessor Organizations
    - General and History, 1928-61, n.d. (Box 90, Folder 1)
    - Proposals, 1893-99 (Box 90, Folder 2)
    - Adjustment Committee
      - Records and minutes, 1895-97 (Box 90, Folder 3-6)
      - Correspondence, 1896-97 (Box 90, Folder 7)
    - Committee on Overtures: report, 1903 (Box 90, Folder 8)
    - 1905-07
      - Joint Committee
        - Correspondence, Jun 1905-Nov 1906 (Box 90, Folder 9-13)
        - Leaflets, circa 1906-07 (Box 90, Folder 14)
        - Summary of Report, 1906 (Box 90, Folder 15)
      - Charter membership, circa 1906 (Box 90, Folder 16)
      - Meetings, conferences, and discussions, 1905-06 (Box 90, Folder 17-18)
      - Reports, proceedings, resolutions, and agreements, Jan 1906-May 1907 (Box 91, Folder 1-3)
      - Sample constitutions and policies, n.d. (Box 91, Folder 4)
      - First Joint Convention, 7 Dec 1906 (Box 91, Folder 5)
- SERIES II. NATIONAL BOARD
  - General, 1907, 1930-2001, n.d. (Box 92, Folder 1-10)
  - Rosters
    - General, 1934-2001, n.d. (Box 92, Folder 11-13)
    - Presidents, 1982, 1996 (Box 92, Folder 14)
  - Committees
    - Executive Committee: general, 1942-55, 1979-93 (Box 93, Folder 1-2)
    - Function of Executive Committee, 1954-55 (Box 93, Folder 3)
    - National Board Nominating Committee, 1964-76, 1985-2000 (Box 93, Folder 4-17)
    - Search Committee for Executive Director, 1974 (Box 93, Folder 18-19)
  - Financial materials
    - 1990-99 (Box 93, Folder 20-22)
    - 2000-02 (Box 94, Folder 1)
  - Honorary Members, 1979, 1984-98 (Box 94, Folder 2)
  - Policies
    - Governance Policies, 1988-1989, 1991, 1994, 1999 (Box 94, Folder 3-4)
    - Policy Research Project, 1988-95 (Box 94, Folder 5)
    - Conflict of interest, 1992-96 (Box 94, Folder 6)
    - Corporate and Social Responsibility, 1979-97, n.d.[see also Ethical Investments Committee] (Box 94, Folder 7)
    - Non-resident members, 1933-45 (Box 94, Folder 8)
    - Rotation of members, 1935-38 (Box 94, Folder 9)
    - Travel, 1982-2000 (Box 94, Folder 10)
  - Publication: Emissaries: A Newsletter for Former National Board Members, 1994-2000 (Box 94, Folder 11)
  - Meetings: National Board and Executive Committee
    - Indexes to National Board minutes
      - General, 1906-1917 (Box 94, Folder 12-14)
      - Defense-related matters, 1937-51 (Box 94, Folder 15)
    - Annual Meeting/Conference of National Board, 1907-18 (Box 94, Folder 16)
    - Regular meetings
      - Dec 1906-1912 (Box 95, Folder 1-11)
      - Jan 1916-Feb 1920 (Box 96, Folder 1-15)
      - Mar 1920- Dec 1922 (Box 97, Folder 1-21)
      - Jan 1923-May 1925 (Box 98, Folder 1-22)
      - Jun 1925-May 1927 (Box 99, Folder 1-16)
      - Oct 1927-Apr 1930 (Box 100, Folder 1-17)
      - May 1930-Dec 1932 (Box 101, Folder 1-22)
      - Jan 1933-Feb 1936 (Box 102, Folder 1-24)
      - Mar 1936-Jan 1939 (Box 103, Folder 1-28)
      - Feb 1939-May 1941 (Box 104, Folder 1-22)
      - Jun 1941-Dec 1943 (Box 105, Folder 1-23)
      - Jan 1944-Oct 1946 (Box 106, Folder 1-27)
      - Nov 1946-Oct 1949 (Box 107, Folder 1-28)
      - Nov 1949-Dec 1952 (Box 108, Folder 1-29)
      - Apr 1953-Mar 1954 (Box 109, Folder 1-16)
      - Apr 1954-Apr 1956 (Box 110, Folder 1-19)
      - May 1956-Nov 1958 (Box 111, Folder 1-20)
      - Dec 1958-Dec 1961 (Box 112, Folder 1-27)
      - Jan 1962-May 1965 (Box 113, Folder 1-25)
      - Sep 1965-Feb 1970 (Box 114, Folder 1-20)
      - Apr 1970-May 1975 (Box 115, Folder 1-16)
      - Oct 1975-Oct 1981 (Box 116, Folder 1-16)
      - Mar 1982-Oct 1991 (Box 117, Folder 1-25)
      - Feb 1992-Oct 1996 (Box 118, Folder 1-15)
      - Feb 1997-Jun 2002 (final meeting) (Box 119, Folder 1-13)
    - Executive Committee, Executive Session, 1944-70 (Box 120, Folder 1-6)
    - National Board, Executive Session, 1971-83 (Box 120, Folder 7)
    - Report of National Board [Recording] Secretary, 1907-14, 1931-69 (Box 120, Folder 8-9)
- SERIES III. NATIONAL COORDINATING BOARD
  - General
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 2002-04 (Box 121, Folder 1)
    - Policies, discussion documents, lists, 2002-03 (Box 121, Folder 2)
  - Committees and Meetings
    - National Coordinating Board: correspondence, minutes, agendas, financial materials, policy drafts, 2002 (Box 121, Folder 3-6)
    - Asset Management and Development Committee: agendas, policies, notes, 2002 (Box 121, Folder 7)
    - Strategic Committees [meetings for organizing strategic committees]
      - Correspondence, notes, policies, 2002 (Box 121, Folder 8)
      - Charters, 2002 (Box 121, Folder 9)
    - Financial
      - Records and notes, 2002 (Box 121, Folder 10)
      - Dues: correspondence and reports, 2000-01 (Box 121, Folder 11)
      - Fiscal agreements, 2001-02 (Box 121, Folder 12)
    - Reorganization
      - General: correspondence, speech, and update, 2000-02 (Box 121, Folder 13)
      - Press releases, 2002 (Box 121, Folder 14)
      - Transition Team: Office relocation project: reports, correspondence, financial materials, 2002 (Box 121, Folder 15)
- SERIES IV. BOARD OF TRUSTEES
  - General and history, 1986-97 (Box 121, Folder 16)
  - By-laws, 1967, 2000 (Box 121, Folder 17)
  - Rosters, 1907-2002 (Box 121, Folder 18-20)
  - Minutes
    - 1907-08, 1910, 1913-25 (Box 121, Folder 21-24)
    - 1926-May 1975 (Box 122, Folder 1-14)
    - May 1984-1998, 2000 (Box 123, Folder 1-14)
  - Committees
    - Rosters, 1988-98 (Box 123, Folder 15)
    - Investment Committee
      - 1985-Aug 1986 (Box 123, Folder 16-21)
      - Oct 1986-2000 (Box 124, Folder 1-19)
    - Nominating Committee, 1992-99, n.d. (Box 124, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1987-98 (Box 124, Folder 21)
  - Restructuring of Association, 2002 (Box 124, Folder 22)
- SERIES V. NATIONAL NOMINATING COMMITTEE
  - General 1940-94, n.d. (Box 125, Folder 1)
  - Task Force on the Nominating Process, 1995 (Box 125, Folder 2)
  - 1948-49 Minutes (Box 125, Folder 3)
  - 1949-52 Notebook (Box 125, Folder 4-5)
  - 1952-55
    - Proceedings of meeting 1 Oct 1954 (Box 125, Folder 6-7)
    - Proceedings of meetings 2-3 Oct 1954 (Box 126, Folder 1-3)
  - 1961-64: proceedings of meeting 9-11 Nov 1963 (Box 126, Folder 4-8)
  - 1964-67
    - Notebook (Box 126, Folder 9)
    - Proceedings of meeting 22-23 Oct 1966 (Box 126, Folder 10-12)
    - Proceedings of meeting 24 Oct 1966 (Box 127, Folder 1)
  - 1970-73
    - Chair's notebook (Box 127, Folder 2-3)
    - Staff resource (Frances Moser) notebook (Box 127, Folder 4)
  - 1985-88 General (Box 127, Folder 5)
  - 1988-91 General (Box 127, Folder 6)
  - 1991-94
    - General (Box 127, Folder 7-8)
    - Biographical data on candidates
      - A-K (Box 127, Folder 9-10)
      - L-Z (Box 128, Folder 1-2)
    - Meeting: packet and minutes, Sep 1993 (Box 128, Folder 3-4)
    - Meeting: packet and minutes, Dec 1993 (Box 128, Folder 5)
    - Conference call, Jan 1994 (Box 128, Folder 6)
  - 1994-96
    - General (Box 128, Folder 7)
    - Meeting packet Dec 1994 (Box 128, Folder 8)
    - Nomination packets, Jan 1995 (Box 128, Folder 9)
    - Mailing, Feb 1995 (Box 128, Folder 10)
    - Meeting packet, Oct 1995 (Box 128, Folder 11)
  - 1996-98
    - Orientation notebook, Jun 1996 General (Box 128, Folder 12)
    - Biographical data on candidates (Box 128, Folder 13-14)
  - 1998-2001 General (Box 128, Folder 15)